A Guide to the Thomas N. Downing Papers, 1947-1977
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Thomas N. Downing Papers, 1947-1977
The Library of Virginia
29773
196.7 cubic feet (562 boxes)
Downing, Thomas N. (Thomas Nelms), 1919-2001
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Military Academy files contain student academic information; they are therefore restricted due to Privacy Act considerations and may not be served. Fourteen cubic feet of records pertaining to the Merchant Marine and Fisheries aspects of Mr. Downing's work have been transferred to the Mariner's Museum in Newport News. Copies of those records are on file at the Library of Virginia. Lists of those records on microfilm are in folders in the collection and are noted in the Contents List.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Hon. Thomas N. Downing, Newport News, 1976.
Biographical Information
Thomas N. Downing served Virginia's First District in the House of Representatives from the 86th through the 94th Congresses. He was the grandson of the late state Senator Thomas J. Downing of Lancaster County (see also Accession Nos. 22035 and 22037, the Downing Family Letters).
Downing was born in Newport News on 1 February 1919. He received his public education in that city, graduating from Newport News High School. He completed his undergraduate education at the Virginia Military Institute, graduating in 1940. During World War II, Downing served as a Combat Troop Commander of Mechanized Cavalry with action in France. He earned a Silver Star for his rescue of two men during a reconnaissance operation in Northern France, and commanded the first of General Patton's Third Army troops to enter Germany. After the war, he earned a law degree from the University of Virginia (1948).
Downing practiced law in Hampton and Warwick, and served as a substitute judge for the Municipal Court for the City of Warwick. In 1958, he won election to the United States House of Representatives as a Democrat. He was elected to the following eight congresses before declining to run for re-election in 1976.
At the time of his retirement, Downing's constituency included seventeen counties (Accomack, Charles City, Essex, Gloucester, James City, King George, King and Queen, King William, Lancaster, Mathews, Middlesex, New Kent, Northampton, Northumberland, Richmond, Westmoreland, and York) and four cities (Hampton, Newport News, Poquoson, and Williamsburg). The geographic and socio-economic nature of the district caused Representative Downing to place special interest and emphasis on such areas as marine life and quality, military and technological affairs, and agricultural considerations; his years of membership on the Merchant Marine and Fisheries and the Space Science and Technology (formerly Science and Astronautics) committees were important vehicles toward serving those interests. Additionally, his advocacy for re-opening the investigations into the assassinations of President John F. Kennedy and Martin Luther King Jr. led to his being appointed the first chairman of the House Select Committee on Assassinations.
After his retirement in 1976, Downing resumed his law practice in Newport News. He was a member of organizations including the American Bar Association, the Lions Club, the American Legion, and the Veterans of Foreign Wars. He served on the Board of Visitors of the Virginia Military Institute, 1985-1993, and as president of the Board of Directors of the Mariner's Museum in Newport News.
Thomas N. Downing died on 23 October 2001 of complications from intestinal surgery, and is buried in Peninsula Memorial Park, Newport News.
The first box of the Downing Papers contains a small group of records from Downing's two immediate predecessors in the First District congressional seat. Schuyler Otis Bland of Gloucester County (1872-1950) served in Congress from 1918 until his death in February 1950. His seat was filled by Edward John Robeson, Jr., who was born in Haywood County, North Carolina (1890), spent his childhood in Georgia, and settled as an adult in Newport News. Robeson served in the 81st through the 85th congresses; he was then defeated for renomination by Thomas Downing. He died in 1966 and is buried in North Carolina.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1947-1977, of Thomas N. Downing (1919-2001) consist of correspondence, political files, speeches, and related documents; they are the public records related to his 18-year tenure as a congressman representing Virginia's First District in the United States House of Representatives. The records include manuscripts, typescripts, xerox, and other reproductions, newsprint, photographs, printed forms (blank and filled in), published items, and other media. The first box of papers contains a small group of records from Downing's two immediate predecessors in the First District seat, Schuyler Otis Bland (1872-1950) and Edward John Robeson, Jr. (1890-1966).
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by congress and, in general, by category. His office's filing system varied in some respects from congress to congress; there are also certain areas of overlap in the filing system (e.g., general legislation appears as a separate category in some congresses, and in conjunction with general files or committee files in other sessions). These instances of overlap or dual filing are reflected in the Preliminary List of Headings and Contents List which follow.
In some cases, record groups extend over several congresses. When that occurred, the groups are placed within this collection with the latest congress with which they deal; i.e. "Rivers and Harbors Materials, 91st-92nd Congresses" is filed with the records for the 92nd Congress. Such multi-congress record groups are also indicated in the Preliminary List of Headings and the Contents List.
Fourteen cubic feet of records pertaining to the Merchant Marine and Fisheries aspects of Mr. Downing's work have been transferred to the Mariner's Museum in Newport News. Copies of those records are on file here at the Library of Virginia. Lists of those records on microfilm are in folders in the collection and are noted in the Contents List.
The preliminary headings are an outline to the contents of the collection, indicating areas of overlapping information by means of brackets (e.g. Committees [and General Legislation]). A detailed listing of the contents of individual boxes follows.
PRELIMINARY LIST OF HEADINGS
Boxes 1-5. S[chuyler] O[tis] B[land] Papers.
Boxes 1-5. Edward J[ohn] Robeson, Jr., Papers.
Boxes 1-5. Campaign for Election to 86th Congress, 1958.
Boxes 5-24. 86th Congress, 1959-1960: [Military] Academies; General Files [and General Legislation]; Invitations; Legislation Introduced and Failed Enactment, 1st and 2nd Sessions; Newspaper Clippings and Publicity; Political Files; Voting Record.
Boxes 24-56. 87th Congress, 1961-1962: [Military] Academies; Committees, General Files [and General Legislation]; Invitations; General Legislation; Legislation Enacted; Legislation Not Enacted; News Releases and Publicity; Political Files; Speech Files; Veterans Affairs, 85th-87th Congresses, 1957-1962; Voting Record.
Boxes 65-101. 88th Congress, 1963-1964: [Military] Academies; General Files; Invitations; General Legislation [and Committees]; Legislation Enacted; Legislation Not Enacted, 1st and 2nd Sessions; Marine Foodstuffs--Information Regarding, various dates; Master Files [1964 only]; Political Files; Veterans Affairs, 1961-1964; Voting Record.
Boxes 101-132. 89th Congress, 1965-1966: [Military] Academies; Committees [and General Legislation]; General Files [and General Legislation]; Invitations; Legislation Enacted; Legislation Not Enacted, 1st and 2nd Sessions; Master Files; Political Files, 1955-1966; Voting Record.
Boxes 132-219. 90th Congress, 1967-1968: [Military] Academies; Committees [and General Legislation]; General Files; Invitations; Legislation Enacted; Legislation Not Enacted, 1st and 2nd Sessions; Master Files; Office Accounts; Political Files, various dates; Post Office and Postmaster Materials, 89th-90th Congresses; Rivers and Harbors Materials, 86th-90th Congresses; Speech Files and Press Releases; Voting Record.
Boxes 219-313. 91st Congress, 1969-1970: [Military] Academies; Committees [and General Legislation]; Federal Installations; General Files; General Reports; Invitations; Legislation Enacted, 1st and 2nd Sessions and General; Legislation Introduced and Failing Enactment, 1st and 2nd Sessions and General; Master Files; Newspaper Clippings and Publicity; Office Accounts; Political Files; Publications and Speeches; [Voting Record omitted].
Boxes 314-407. 92nd Congress, 1971-1972: [Military] Academies; Committees [and General Legislation]; Federal Installations; General Files; Invitations; Legislation Enacted, 1st and 2nd Sessions and General; Legislation Introduced and Failing Enactment, 1st and 2nd Sessions and General; Master Files; Newspaper Clippings and Publicity; Office Accounts; Political Files; Rivers and Harbors Materials, 91st-92nd Congresses; Speech Files; Voting Reocrd.
Boxes 407-479. 93rd Congress, 1973-1974: [Military] Academies; Committees [and General Legislation]; Federal Installations; General Files; Invitations; Legislation Enacted; Legislation Not Enacted; Master Files; Newspaper Clippings and Publicity; Political Files; Post Office Files, 92nd-93rd Congresses; Speech Files; Voting Record.
Boxes 479-557. 94th Congress, 1975-1976: [Military] Academies; Committees [and General Legislation]; General Files [and Federal Installations]; Invitations; Legislation Enacted; Legislation Not Enacted; Master Files; Newspaper Clippings and Publicity; Political Files; Speech Files; Voting Record.
Boxes 557-562. Speech Files, Undated and Unspecified Congress.
Contents List
- S[chuyler] O[tis] B[land] Papers, 1st District Congressman, 1918-1950. (Box 1)
  - Atlantic Charter and Atlantic Pact--International Subjects.
  - Atlantic Charter--Public Affairs File--General.
  - Peninsula Executives' Club, 1947.
  - Portrait of William Pitt.
  - Stratford Hall.
  - United Nations--International Subjects.
  - Virginia, Commonwealth of.
  - Wakefield.
- Edward J[ohn] Robeson, Jr., Papers, 1st District Congressman, 1950-1959. (Box 1)
  - Waltrip, Brizendine, Skillman, and Rowe--Relief for, 1954-1960.
  - World Calendar Legislation, 1955.
- Campaign for Election to 86th Congress, 1958. (Box 1)
  - Political files, A-C. (2 folders)
- Campaign for Election to 86th Congress, 1958. (Box 2)
  - Political files, D-Z. (8 folders)
- Campaign for Election to 86th Congress, 1958. (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, February-September 1958. (3 folders)
  - Miscellaneous files.
    - Accomack County
    - Charles City County
    - Essex County
    - Gloucester County
    - Hampton County
    - King and Queen County
    - Middlesex County
    - Newport News
    - Northampton County
    - Princess Anne County
    - Warwick
    - Williamsburg
    - York County
  - General file--Speeches, etc. (2 folders)
- Campaign for Election to 86th Congress, 1958. (Box 4)
  - Speeches--General, before 1959.
  - States' Rights Material.
  - Democratic Primary, July 1958.
  - Downing for Congress, Democratic Primary, July 1958.
  - Correspondence, A-L. (2 folders)
- Campaign for Election to 86th Congress, 1958. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, M-Z. (2 folders)
  - Correspondence--Batches.
  - Miscellaneous campaign materials, various dates. (2 folders)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 5)
  - [Military] Academies.
    Note: The Military Academy Files contain complete applications, including scholastic records, medical records, etc.; these records cannot be served. Student records are restricted because of Privacy Act considerations.
    - Candidates for Air Force Academy, 1959
    - Air Force Academy, 1960
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 6)
  - [Military] Academies.
    Note: Military Academy Files contain student academic information; they are therefore restricted due to Privacy Act considerations and may not be served.
    - Merchant Marine Academy, 1960
    - Military Academy, 1959-1960 (2 folders)
    - Naval Academy, 1959-1960 (2 folders)
    - Civil Service Examinations for Applicants
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 7)
  - [Military] Academies.
    - Out-of-District Applicants
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Agricultural Legislation
    - Alcoholic Beverages
    - Arlington National Cemetery--Acreage
    - Armed Services Legislation (2 folders)
    - Automobile Dealers Territorial Legislation
    - Banking Legislation
    - Budget
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 8)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Canners Legislation
    - Civil Rights Legislation
    - Civil Service Retirement
    - Commitment File
    - Connally Amendment
    - Credit Union Legislation
    - District of Columbia Legislation
    - Educational Legislation
    - Equal Rights Legislation
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 9)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Foreign Aid
    - Freight Forwarders Legislation
    - Gallery Card--Publications
    - General Legislation (2 folders)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 10)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - General Legislation (1 folder)
    - Hawaii Statehood
    - Highway Legislation
    - Home Rule--D.C.
    - Housing Legislation (2 folders)
    - Immigration Legislation
    - Import and Export Legislation
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 11)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Labor Legislation (3 folders)
    - General Labor Legislation
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 12)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Labor Reform Legislation (3 folders)
    - Fair Labor Standards Act (1 folder)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 13)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Fair Labor Standards Act (1 folder)
    - Library Services Bill
    - Lighthouse Service
    - Medical Legislation
    - Merchant Marine and Fisheries.
      Note: Merchant Marine and Fisheries legislation is on microfilm; see list in folder.
    - National Flower
    - National Guard Legislation
    - Postal Inspection
    - Price Legislation
    - Racial Legislation
    - Railroad Legislation
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 14)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Rural Electrification
    - School Integration
    - Small Business Legislation (3 folders)
    - Social Security Legislation
    - Stationery Account
    - Stoermer, Robert L.
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 15)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Tax Legislation (2 folders)
    - Tennessee Valley Authority [TVA]
    - Trade Legislation
    - T[ele]V[ision] Legislation
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 16)
  - General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Un-American Activities Committee
    - Unemployment Benefits
    - Veterans Legislation
    - Water Pollution Legislation
  - Invitations.
    - Invitations Accepted, January-April 1959 (4 folders)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 17)
  - Invitations.
    - Invitations Accepted, May-December 1959 (8 folders)
    - Invitations Declined, January-May 1959 (5 folders)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 18)
  - Invitations.
    - Invitations Declined, June-December 1959 (7 folders)
    - Invitations Accepted, January-August 1960 (4 folders)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 19)
  - Invitations.
    - Invitations Accepted, September-December 1960 (4 folders)
    - Invitations Declined, January-June 1960 (6 folders)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 20)
  - Invitations.
    - Invitations Declined, July-December 1960 (6 folders)
    - Invitations Extended by Mr. Downing, 86th Congress
  - Legislation Introduced and Failed Enactment, 1st Session.
    - Bland, Mrs. S. Otis
    - Brooks, Willie Lemuel
    - National Debt Reduction
  - Legislation Introduced and Failed Enactment, 2nd Session.
    - Brown, Walter L.
    - Forrest, Charles B.
    - Woodrow Wilson Memorial
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 21)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Publicity.
    - January-December 1959 (3 folders)
    - January-April 1960 (1 folders)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 22)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Publicity.
    - May-September 1960 (2 folders)
    - News Releases
    - Your Congressman Reports, 86th Congress
  - Political Files.
    - Doctors in First District
    - Accomack--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - Charles City--Contacts
    - Essex--Contacts
    - Gloucester--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 23)
  - Political Files.
    - Hampton--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - James City--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - King and Queen--Contacts
    - Mathews--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - Middlesex--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - New Kent--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - Newport News--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - Northampton--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - Princess Anne--Contacts
    - Virginia Beach--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - Williamsburg--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - York--Contacts and Campaign Clippings (2 folders)
    - Out-of-District Campaign Letters
    - Democratic National Convention, Los Angeles, California
    - State Democratic Convention, Virginia Beach
- 86th Congress, 1959-1960. (Box 24)
  - Political Files.
    - Campaign Procedure, 1960
    - Presidential Campaign, 1960
    - Petitions, 1960
    - Congratulations
    - Democratic Congressional Committee
    - Electoral College
  - Voting Record.
    - 1st and 2nd Sessions
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 24)
  - [Military] Academies.
    - Air Force Academy, 1961
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 25)
  - [Military] Academies.
    - Air Force Academy, 1962
    - Merchant Marine Academy, 1961-1962 (2 folders)
    - King's Point Merchant Marine Academy Correspondence
    - Military Academy, 1961-1962 (3 folders)
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 26)
  - [Military] Academies.
    - Military Academy--General Correspondence
    - Naval Academy, 1961-1962 (2 folders)
    - Naval Academy--General Correspondence
    - Naval Academy Nominees, 1961
    - Nominees and Nomination Information
    - Preparatory Schools
    - Withdrawn Applicant File
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 27)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Agriculture (4 folders)
    - Aids to Navigation
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 28)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Civil Service (2 folders)
    - Claims
    - Davis, Jefferson
    - Debates--High School and College
    - Delinquent Accounts
    - Delmarva--Economic Development
    - Disaster Relief
    - Disaster Relief--Hurricane Donna
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 29)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Downing Notes (from Hampton Office)
    - D--General
    - Eastern Shore
    - Education (2 folders)
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 30)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Education Legislation--Impacted Areas
    - Employee Compensation
    - Extension of Remarks
    - E--General
    - Federal Aviation Administration [FAA]
    - Federal Communications Commission [FCC]
    - FCC Rule--Daytime Broadcasting
    - Federal Grants
    - Federal Trade Commission [FTC]
    - Ferguson Corporation
    - First District
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 31)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Fish
    - Fish Hatcheries--1st District
    - Fishing Restrictions, Fish Stakes, Etc.
    - Flags
    - Football Tickets, 1961
    - Forestry
    - Fork Union Military Academy
    - F--General
    - Gallery Passes, 1st and 2nd Sessions (2 folders)
    - General Services Administration [GSA]
    - Girl Scouts of Administration
    - G--General
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 32)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Housing--General (2 folders)
    - Housing--FHA Rejection of Subdivisions on the Peninsula
    - Immigration and Naturalization--General
    - Immigration and Naturalization--Hungarian Teenagers
    - Merchant Marine and Fisheries.
      Merchant Marine and Fisheries legislation is on microfilm; see list in folder.
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 33)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Migratory Labor
    - National Aeronautics and Space Administration [NASA] (2 folders)
    - NASA News Releases--Space Committee
    - Publications Received (2 folders)
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 34)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Public Welfare
    - Railroads
    - Railroad Retirement
    - Redistricting, 1961
    - Reed, Dr. Walter
    - Residual Fuel Oil Imports
    - Resolutions--Commonwealth of Virginia
    - Roads--General
    - Roads--RAMP--Newport News Highway #64
    - Roads--Highway 64--General
    - Roads--Route 617
    - Roads--Shirley Highway--Insterstate Route 95
    - Roads--Virginia Beach Highway
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 35)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Roosevelt, Theodore
    - Rules Committee
    - Rural Electrification
    - R--General
    - Saline Water Selection
    - Scholarships
    - Science and Astronautics Committee
    - Securities and Exchange Commission [SEC]
    - Shepard Convention Center
    - Shipbuilders Council of America
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 36)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Shoreline Protection
    - Sightseeing
    - Small Business
    - Social Security (2 folders)
    - Speakers
    - State Department
    - Steel Price Increase, 1962
    - Stewart, Donald
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 37)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Supreme Court
    - Surplus Food
    - Surplus Property
    - S--General (2 folders)
    - Tangier
    - Tangier Beach Erosion
    - Tappahannock
    - Tariffs
    - Taxes (2 folders)
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 38)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Taxes (2 folders)
    - Tractors for Freedom
    - Trade Mission Program
    - T--General
    - Unemployment Compensation
    - Unidentified Flying Objects
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 39)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - United Nations
    - United States Territories and Possessions
    - University of Virginia
    - Urban Renewal Administration--Joint Highway
    - Veterans Organizations
    - Victory Arch
    - Virginia Beach
    - Virginia Beach Erosion Commission
    - Virginia Farm Bureau
    - Virginia General Assembly
    - Virginia Manufacturers Association
    - Virginia Marine Laboratory
    - Virginia Military Institute [VMI]
    - Virginia Peninsula Industrial Committee
    - Virginia Pilots Association
    - Virginia Polytechnic Institute [VPI]
    - Virginia Society
    - Virginia State Board of Hairdressers and Cosmetology
    - Virginia State Chamber of Commerce
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 40)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - Virginia State Parks
    - Virginia State Ports Authority
    - Virginia Travel Bureau and Virginia Travel Council
    - Vocational Rehabilitation
    - Voice of America
    - U, V--General
    - War Memorial Museum, Newport News
    - Waterford
    - Weather Bureau
    - Western Union
    - White House Tours
    - College of William and Mary
    - Colonial Williamsburg, Inc.
- 87th Congress, 1961-1962. (Box 41)
  - Committees, General Files [and General Legislation].
    - W--General (2 folders)
    - York County
    - Yorktown
    - Yorktown Bridge
    - Yorktown Day Celebration, October 19
    - Yorktown Festival Day
    - Yorktown Memorial
    - Yorktown Monument
    - Yorktown Park--Colonial National Historical Park
    - YMCA
  - Invitations.